Guide to the Norman D. Rabinovitz Photograph Collection, 1965-1999 AIS.2010.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Norman D. Rabinovitz Photograph Collection
1965-1999
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rabinovitz, Norman D.
AIS.2010.16
10.25 Linear Feet (13,940 items)
The Norman D. Rabinovitz Photograph Collection largely comprises the images he took as a medical photographer at Allegheny General Hospital and Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh, now UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh. His medical photography covers broad topics ranging from physicians to surgical procedures, hospitalized children, and medical equipment. The collection also documents his work as a photographer for University of Pittsburgh archaeological digs, his travels, photo experimentation, and Pittsburgh among other topics.
Related Material
In 2011 Mr. Rabinovitz donated photographs specifically relating to the Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh to the hospital.
Biography
Norman D. Rabinovitz was born in 1935 in the Hill District neighborhood of Pittsburgh and grew up on Bryn Mawr Road.
After high school, Rabinovitz entered the University of Pittsburgh to study philosophy. He was drafted into the Air Force where he served for four years, teaching photography at the Air Force Service Club. Upon his return to Pitt, he changed his study to communications. Teaching and sharing his knowledge of photography was important to Rabinovitz even after his work with the Air Force. Once back in Pittsburgh he taught courses at the Brashear Association, the Kingsley Association, and the Art Institute of Pittsburgh as well as in the Free University program sponsored by the University of Pittsburgh.
Rabinovitz was hired as a medical photographer at Allegheny General Hospital in 1962. After one year there, he moved to the Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh in 1963. He remained at Children's for 38 years where he retired as director of medical photography. His medical photography covered broad topics ranging from physicians to surgical procedures, hospitalized children, and medical equipment. He was also an occasional photographer for the local newspaper, Oakland. Additionally, Rabinovitz participated as a photographer for University of Pittsburgh archaelogical digs excavating Neolithic pits at Öcsöd-Kovashalom, which took place in 1971. He was an avid experimenter in photographic techniques, becoming called upon to test new products such as Kodak's infrared film and Polaroid's Polachrome.
While Rabinovitz has contributed much to photography on a world-wide scale, one of his significant accomplishments was in saving the work of noted photographer Esther Bubley from the dumpster. His rescue of her Children's Hospital photographs, taken in 1951 when Bubley was part of the Pittsburgh Photographic Library project, helped preserve them. By bringing Bubley's photographs to the attention of local documentary filmmaker Ken Love and his wife, pediatrician Barbara McNulty, MD, the award winning documentary, That's Pediatrics, was able to be made. Rabinovitz's association with Ken Love led to collaborations on a film on the life and work of Samuel Rosenberg and photographer, Charles "Teenie" Harris. Rabinovitz also collaborated with friends and fellow photographers Herb Ferguson, Stephan Lorant, Eugene Smith, and Roy Stryker. He also collaborated with Dr. Sylvan Stool on films relating to otoscopy.
Rabinovitz has been a member of the Royal Photographic Society, and a Photomicroscopist. His photography has appeared in several books and journals including:
Rubin, Judith Aron. Art therapy: an introduction. Philadelphia, PA: Brunner/Mazel, 1999.
Rubin, Judith Aron, and Judith Aron Rubin. Introduction to art therapy: sources & resources .New York: Routledge, 2010.
Bernardo, Lisa Marie, Marianne Bove, and Raymond B. Karasic. Pediatric emergency nursing procedures. Boston: Jones and Bartlett, 1993.
Rabinovits lives in Pittsburgh with his wife Nancy.
Scope and Content Notes
The Norman D. Rabinovitz Photograph Collection contains photos and other items dating from 1965 to 1999. The collection contains approximately 13,940 items found in a variety of formats including photographic prints, color and black and white negatives, 35mm slides, and manuscript materials. Because of overlapping subjects contained within some groups of photographs, it was not possible to separate them according to topic. They remain as organized by the photographer.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Norman D. Rabinovitz Photograph Collection, 1965-1999, AIS.2010.16, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
This collection contains ten series:
Series I. Roy Stryker
Series II. Medical
Series III. Pittsburgh
Series IV. Travel
Series V. University of Pittsburgh Archaelogical Dig
Series VI. Photographic Experimentation
Series VII. Nature Photography
Series VIII. Topical
Series IX. Manuscript Materials
Series X. Oversized Materials
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Norman D. Rabinovitz in 2011.
Dover (England) -- Photographs; Switzerland -- Photographs; Greece -- Photographs; Turkey -- Photographs; France -- Photographs; University of Pittsburgh; Yugoslavia -- Photographs; Washington (D.C.) -- Photographs; Green Turtle Cay (Bahamas) -- Photographs; Amsterdam (Netherlands) -- Photographs; Cayman Islands -- Photographs; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Photographs; Travel photography; Photography; Photography of animals; Medical Photography; Nature photography; Spain -- Photographs; London (England) -- Photographs; PNC Park (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh -- Photographs; Stryker, Roy Emerson
- Roy Stryker, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The materials in this series document his interest in the work of noted photographer, Roy Stryker. Items include photographs taken of Roy Stryker, articles written about Stryker, and materials relating to photographic projects on which Stryker worked.
  - Notes and Materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pittsburgh Rivers- Roy Stryker in Pittsburgh- Pittsburgh Skyline (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh Rivers Project (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - News Articles Related to Roy Stryker (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Medical, II.
  The images in this series document medical procedures and medical life as well as surgeries, x-rays, testing, cells, and physicians.
  - Offices, Rooms, Buildings, Personel (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Surgeries (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Blood Work (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Under the microscope and x-rays (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Emergency vehicles and helicopters (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Pittsburgh, III.
  The images in this series document Pittsburgh. Views include Three Rivers Stadium, the University of Pittsburgh, various Pittsburgh neighborhoods such as Downtown, Oakland, and the South Side, Nine Mile Run development, the Pittsburgh Folk Festival, Stouffer's Restaurant, railroads, sporting events, and other topics.
  - Famous Visitors, ca. 1970s-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes Paul Simon, Ike and Tina Turner, Nancy Reagan, Debbie Reynolds, and Gloria Steinem among others.
  - Pittsburgh Symphony- Andre Previn and Itzhak Perlman (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railway Yard (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Point Park (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - PNC Park (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - World Series, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Implostion of Carlton House Hotel, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cathedral of Learning and Oakland Views (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - University of Pittsburgh Law School Construction (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pitt Stadium, Three Rivers Stadium, Forbes Field (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pitt Stadium, Three Rivers Stadium, and Forbes Field (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - University of Pittsburgh Swimming and Diving (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - University of Pittsburgh Football (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Children's Hospital (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Downtown Pittsburgh, 1970-1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Stouffer's Restaurant (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gateway Center (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mount Washington (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - South Side (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - First Unitarian Church (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 9 Mile Run Development (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pittsburgh Folk Festival, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pittsburgh Youth Orchestra (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Circus (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Pittsburgh Views (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wesley Posvar and Sarah Heinz (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - University of Pittsburgh Medical School (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Urban Redevelopment (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Portraits (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Portraits of Dr. Mark Ravich, Albert Ferguson, Phil Fireman, and Dr, Henry T. Bahnson.
  - Nurses (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Travel, IV.
  The images in this series contain travel photographs of monuments, people, various locations in the United States as well as the Cayman Islands, Spain, Yugoslavia, Greece, Turkey, England, and Switzerland.
  - Washington D.C. & Other U.S. Locations (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Spain, Yugoslavia, France, Greece (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Spain (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Green Turtle Cay, Bahamas (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - London and Dover, England, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Switzerland (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Istanbul and Diyarbakır, Turkey, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Pamploma and Andorra Spain, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Yugoslavia (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Greece and Turkey (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - France (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cayman Islands, July 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Amsterdam, Denmark and France (Box 2, Folder 6)
- University of Pittsburgh Archaelogical Dig, 1971; V.
  This series contains images documenting a University of Pittsburgh archeological dig excavating Neolithic pits at Öcsöd-Kovashalom, which took place in 1971. Included are views of artifacts, the dig, and those who participated in the project.
  - Archeological Dig, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographic Experimentation, VI.
  The images in this series document Rabinovitz's work with photographic experimentation in a variety of settings and using various techniques to achieve the desired effects.
  - Movement and Motion (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Special Effects (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Heinz Chapel Experiment (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reflection (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Depth of Field (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Contrast (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Edwin Land Experiment (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Color Separation Portraits (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Color (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Crashing Bulb in Motion (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Kaliedescope images (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Infrared (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - x-rayed (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Old Church Study (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mushroom (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - City Shots (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lightning (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Early American Room (Cathedral of Learning, University of Pittsburgh) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Unknown (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Nature Photography, VII.
  This series includes images of plants and animal life.
  - Plant Life (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Animal Life (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
- Topical, VIII.
  The images in this series cover many subjects including animals, inanimate objects, plant life, city shots, advertisements and people. Several are copy photographs taken for projects. These items bear no description or collection origination information.
  - Unidentified Locations (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Advertisements (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Topical Images (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Blended Glass and Fireworks (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Construction and Metal Work (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Union Volkswagon and Car show (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bird Banding and Old Time Cooking (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Holocaust Museum-Survivor and Child (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Music Performances (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Images of People (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Linda Comis (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Winston Churchill (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Antique Collectables (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Personal, 35mm B&W Negatives (Box 3, Folder 13)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying 35mm black and white negatives. Subjects covered include nature, archaeology, Pittsburgh, and photographic experimentation. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Personal Negatives (Box 3, Folder 14)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying negatives. Subjects covered include photo experimentation, Pittsburgh images. An original note indicated that these may have been items Rabinovitz wished to print. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Misc. 35mm Slides (Box 3, Folder 15)
    This group contains 35mm slides covering a variety of subjects and photographic experimentation Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Misc. 35mm B&W Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying negatives. Subjects covered include animal life, photographic experimentation, traveling, and other topical images. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Misc. 35mm Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying 35mm negatives. Topics covered include travel, archeology, medical, nature, photographic experimentation. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Misc. 35mm Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 3, Folder 20)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying 35mm negatives. Subjects covered include photographic experimentation, copy photography, and travel. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Misc. 120mm Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 3, Folder 21)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying negatives. Subjects covered include photographic experimentation, the University of Pittsburgh, nature, and copy photography. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Misc. B&W Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 3, Folder 22)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying negatives. Subjects covered include medical, photographic experimentation, nature, travel. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Negatives and Tranparencies (Box 3, Folder 23)
    This group contains contact sheets and accompanying negatives. Subjects covered include nature, Pittsburgh, and travel. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Special Slides (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    This group contains 35mm slides, contact sheets, and accompanying negatives. Subjects covered include medical, photographic experimentation, Pittsburgh, and travel. Because many subjects appear together on the same contact sheets and sleeves, they remain as orginzed by the photographer.
  - Presentation Slides, Pittsburgh in the Civil War (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Presentation Slides, Understanding Photography (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Copy Photographs (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Unidentified copy photographs taken for projects. No specific collection or original owner is identified.
- Manuscript Materials, IX.
  This series contains manuscript materials that includes documentation surrounding the University of Pittsburgh archeological dig on which he particapted as photographer, journal articles for which Norman Rabinowitz provided photographs, journal articles and papers he wrote, research materials, and correspondence.
  - Paper Negatives Revisited By Allison Drash and Norman D. Rabinovitz, September 15, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, March 15, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Letters to to Norman Rabinovitz from Robert G. Wydo.
  - Letter from Frederic M. Vogelsang (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Letter Regarding Equipment Used in Yugoslavian Archeological Dig, June 30, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Three Rivers Action Development Committee (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Journal of Housing No.5, May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Journal of Audiovisual Media in Medicine Vol. 8 No.1, January 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Partners for Pre-Eminence Newsletters (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Alumni Times Newspaper Vol.6 No.4, Winter 1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Times Newspaper Vol.11 No. 2, Summer 1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh in the Civil War Slide Show list (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Endoscopic Cinematography a rticle by Norman D. Rabinovitz & Sylvan E. Stool, April 1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Report of Activities in 1970 and Request for Additional Support- Smithsonian Institution Foreign Currency Program, October 1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Pamphlet, Art Awareness Workshops for Teachers in Environmental Education, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - A Diagnostic Art Interview Judith A. Rubin, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Route to the Mastoid Antrum Sylvan E. Stool, M.D., & Keith H. Riding, M.D., July 1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Lecture Notes, Introduction to Dye Transfer (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Dye Is Quicker Than The Eye, February 2,1975 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Cover story from The Pittsburgh Press Roto magazine.
- Oversized Materials, X.
  This series contains oversized versions of images that can be found throughout the collection. These include an autographed picture of Roy Stryker addressed to Norman Rabinowitz and views of renovations to "The Bank" which is now the Point Park University Library.
  - Oversized Materials (Box 5-8)
  - Ringling Brothers (Map-case 13, Drawer 20, Folder 1)
  - Graphite Sketch, Yugoslavian Woman, 1980 (Map-case 13, Drawer 20, Folder 2)